<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<typeSystemDescription xmlns="http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier">
	<name>Metadata</name>
	<description/>
	<version>${version}</version>
	<vendor>Ubiquitous Knowledge Processing (UKP) Lab, Technische Universität Darmstadt</vendor>
	<types>
		<typeDescription>
			<name>de.tudarmstadt.ukp.dkpro.core.api.metadata.type.DocumentMetaData</name>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;The DocumentMetaData annotation stores information about a single processed
document. There can only be one of these annotations per CAS. The annotation is
created by readers and contains information to uniquely identify the document from
which a CAS was created. Writer components use this information when determining
under which filename a CAS is stored.&lt;p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two principle ways of identifying a document:&lt;p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;collection id / document id:&lt;/b&gt; this simple system identifies a document
  within a collection. The ID of the collection and the document are each
  simple strings without any further semantics such as e.g. a hierarchy. For
  this reason, this identification scheme is not well suited to preserve
  information about directory structures.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;document base URI / document URI:&lt;/b&gt; this system identifies a document using
  a URI. The base URI is used to derive the relative path of the document with
  respect to the base location from where it has been read. E.g. if the base
  URI is &lt;code&gt;file:/texts&lt;/code&gt; and the document URI is &lt;code&gt;file:/texts/english/text1.txt&lt;/code&gt;, then the relativ
  path of the document is &lt;code&gt;english/text1.txt&lt;/code&gt;. This
  information is used by writers to recreate the directory structure found
  under the base location in the target location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible and indeed common for a writer to initialize both systems of
identification. If both systems are present, most writers default to using the
URI-based systems. However, most writers also allow forcing the use of the ID-based
systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the features given here, there is a &lt;i&gt;language&lt;/i&gt; feature inherited from UIMA's DocumentAnnotation. DKPro Core components expect a two letter ISO
639-1 language code there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<supertypeName>uima.tcas.DocumentAnnotation</supertypeName>
			<features>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>documentTitle</name>
					<description>The human readable title of the document.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>documentId</name>
					<description>The id of the document.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>documentUri</name>
					<description>The URI of the document.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>collectionId</name>
					<description>The ID of the whole document collection.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>documentBaseUri</name>
					<description>Base URI of the document.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
				<featureDescription>
					<name>isLastSegment</name>
					<description>CAS de-multipliers need to know whether a CAS is the
						last multiplied segment.
						Thus CAS multipliers should set this field to true for the last CAS
						they produce.</description>
					<rangeTypeName>uima.cas.Boolean</rangeTypeName>
				</featureDescription>
			</features>
		</typeDescription>
		</types>
</typeSystemDescription>
